Guide to the Cornwall Educators Collection 1881-1943 MS013 MS013 MS013
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Educators Collection
1881-1943
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS013
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
This collection contains items related to Cornwall educators.
Provenance
The majority of items were collected by Cornwall historians E.C. Starr and Emily E. Marsh.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"Educators who were from the community, or descended from local families, include Edward Chauncey Baldwin (1870-1940). Baldwin taught as a professor at the University of Illinois. Kenyon Chamberlain (unknown-unknown) was also a native of Cornwall and well-known entomologist. Mary W. Chapin (1820-1889) descended from Cornwall families and graduated at Mt. Holyoke College, where she also later taught. Joseph E. Whitney (1858-1893) was born in Cornwall, and edited The Cornwall Star in addition to his teaching duties at Yale. Latin teacher Alfred H. T. Bacon (1893-after 1940) was not from the community, but married into the Cornwall Calhoun family. Educators who moved to the community include John Catlin (unknown-unknown) who taught in the public schools for several years. Dr. William C. Clarke (1872-1941) taught at Columbia University before moving to Cornwall. Rowland E. Leach (unknown-unknown) taught choral lessons in Cornwall before moving west to Illinois. Granville D. Wilson taught at the Young Ladies Institute in Johnson Hollow, which was also known as the "Bird’s Nest." The Woolsey family were summer residents of the community. Theodore Dwight Woolsey (1801-1889) served as the president of Yale, and his son, Theodore Salisbury Woolsey (1852-1929), also taught at the college. The connections that G.A. Burggraf, Henry B. Learned, and E. P. St. John had to Cornwall are unknown."
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains items related to Cornwall educators. Teachers who were from Cornwall, as well as individuals who moved to the community are all represented in this collection. The majority of items were collected by Cornwall historians E.C. Starr and Emily E. Marsh.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into one series. Within each the series, papers are organized chronologically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Teacher's Meetings
General Information
Teachers
Cornwall (Conn.)--Education.; Correspondence; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Cornwall Historical Society
- Teacher’s Meetings
  - Meeting programs, 1892-1907; , undated (Box 1, Folder 1'-6)
- General Information.
  - Correspondence with E.C. Starr regarding contemporary Cornwall teachers, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - E.C. Starr’s list of Cornwall teachers, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Suggestions to the Teacher," lesson book, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Table of teachers’ salaries in Connecticut, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List of Cornwall school teachers, districts unknown, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Teachers
  - Theodore Salisbury Woolsey
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr regarding Dibble French and Indian War diary, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - History of the New Haven Bank, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Obituary, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Theodore Dwight Woolsey
    - Article, "Death of Two Daughters of President Woolsey", 1870 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Memorial items, 1889-1890; , undated (Box 1, Folder 66-69)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr by Woolsey’s daughter, about her father’s writings, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Newspaper image, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Professor Granville D. Wilson
    - Memorial articles, 1897; , undated (Box 1, Folder 60-62)
    - Correspondence between E.C. Starr and Mrs. G.D. Wilson, about her husband’s work at the "Bird’s Nest" school, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "Catalogue of Instrumental and Vocal Compositions," by G.D. Wilson, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Joseph Ernest Whitney
    - "The Horoscope" newsletter, mentioning candidacy for Skull and Bones, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Yale Banner edited by Whitney, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Poems, 1882-1894 (Box 1, Folder 38-43)
    - Yale course catalogue, listing course taught by Whitney, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Publications, 1888-1892 (Box 1, Folder 45-47)
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr regarding life in Colorado, illness, and faith, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
    - Death notices, 1893, , undated (Box 1, Folder 50-55)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding the "Ernest Whitney Boy’s Club", 1895; , undated (Box 1, Folder 56-57)
    - Article about Yale English Department, mentioning Whitney, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Envelope for The Cornwall Star, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Professor E.P. St. John
    - Blurb in "The Silver Trumpet", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Professor Henry Barrett Learned
    - "Correspondence," in The Nation, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "Annual Report of the Civic Federation of New Haven, Connecticut," mentioning Learned, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Rowland E. Leach
    - Booklet about career as violin soloist and teacher, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, about Cornwall Chorus, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Program for recital, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Regnar Kiddle
    - Notice for "vocal instruction" taught by Kiddle, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dr. William C. Clarke
    - Obituary, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mary W. Chapin
    - Letters sent to E.C. Starr from Mt. Holyoke College regarding Chapin’s career, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Kenton F. Chamberlain
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about church membership, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Publications, 1920-1931 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
    - Autograph, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - John Catlin
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, regarding former job in Cornwall, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - G. A. Burggraf
    - Program mentioning G.A. Burggraf at Central Baptist Church in New York, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T. R. Baldwin
    - Card for singing school taught by Baldwin, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Edward Chauncey Baldwin
    - Publications, 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper article about new book, Our Modern Debt to Israel, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Biographical information, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Alfred H. T. Bacon
    - Biographical profile, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)